[
  {
    "question": "Concerning of the roles of ITAM and ITIM in regulating immune response, which statement is true?",
    "options": {
      "A": "ITAMs and ITIMs, negatively and positively, respectively regulate immune response.",
      "B": "PD-1 has ITAMs, so anti-PD-1 can activate T-cell, allowing the killing of tumor cells and serving as immune therapeutic treatment.",
      "C": "An TCR has 6 ITAMs on its inter membrane side.",
      "D": "Lck, a serine kinase family member, requires CD45."
    },
    "answer": null,
    "explanation": "1. 無解\n(A) 相反。ITAM (activation)可促進免疫反應，ITIM (inhibition)可抑制免疫反應。\n(B) PD1 有 ITIM，因此 anti-PD-1 可防止 ITIM 抑制 T cell，促進 T cell 殺死癌細胞。\n(C) TCR 本身並沒有 ITAM。TCR complex 的 ITAM 來自 ζ 鏈的 6 個，加上兩組 CD3 各自帶的 2 個 ITAM，總共 10 個 ITAM。\n(D) Lck 為 tyrosine kinase。Lck 本為磷酸化 (去活化) 狀態。TCR 接觸抗原時，CD45 會將 Lck 上的 pTyr 去磷酸化，活化 Lck。"
  },
  {
    "question": "CAR-T and immune checkpoint blockade are two breakthroughs in recent years. Which of the statements concerning two approaches is correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "CAR-T approach bypasses the requirement of the recognition of MHC peptide and 2 signals to activate antigen-presenting-T cell.",
      "B": "Immune checkpoint blockade is to block the molecules that transduce inhibiting signals in antigen presenting cells.",
      "C": "CAR-T and immune checkpoint blockade both work for solid tumor and leukemia efficiently.",
      "D": "The mechanism for anti-CTLA-4 and anti-PD-1 immune checkpoint blockade is the same; therefore, there is no increased therapeutic activity when doing combined treatment."
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "2. (A)\n(A) 正確。\n(B) 不是擋住抗原呈現細胞，是擋住免疫細胞 (T cell) 的抑制訊號受體，讓 T cell 不會被抑制。\n(C) CAR-T 目前僅針對 leukemia 或其他血液腫瘤治療，尚未能應用至固體腫瘤治療。\n(D) Anti-CTLA-4 與 Anti-PD-1 的作用機轉不完全相同。Anti-CTLA-4 是針對 T cell 接受抗原呈現時，擋住 CTLA-4 受器，使抗原呈現細胞的 B7 結合 T cell 的 CD28，活化 T cell。Anti-CD-1 則是針對 T cell 接觸癌細胞時，擋住 T cell 的 PD-1 受器，使其不會被癌細胞的 PD-L1 抑制。兩種藥一起使用可能可以增強效果，但也更可能有自體免疫的副作用。"
  },
  {
    "question": "AMPs belong to a component of innate immune system. Which statement concerning AMPs is CORRECT?",
    "options": {
      "A": "AMPs are produced by non-immune cells in skins, lungs and guts where the host is exposed directly to the outside environment and by some innate cells.",
      "B": "AMPs are produced in an active form and can kill bacteria immediately.",
      "C": "AMPs are peptides with a hydrophobic end and a hydrophilic end, which will kill the cell wall of bacteria.",
      "D": "AMPs have selective killing ability toward bacteria but not host cell."
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "3. (A)\n(A) AMPs 由上皮組織與吞噬細胞製造。如：皮膚中的 stratum spinosum、腸上皮中的 Paneth cell。\n(B) AMPs 製造出來時通常處於不活化狀態 (Pro-AMP)，需要經蛋白酶切割 pro-region 後才能作用，稱為 proteolysis。\n(C) AMPs 為親疏水兩重性 (amphipathic) 多肽，可以穿入細胞膜並形成穿孔，不是細胞壁。\n(D) AMPs 不具專一性。當細菌出現時，Pro-AMP 才會被切割活化，因此才不會殺死 host cell。另一種說法是，細菌細胞膜的結構相對於 host cell 更容易吸引 AMPS。"
  },
  {
    "question": "The complement system is crucial for the host to defend against bacterial infection. Which of the following concerning activation and function of complement is correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "The classical pathway and lectin pathway both generate C3 convertase C4b2a. The structure of the Clr and Cls are similar to the MBL.",
      "B": "MBL and ficolins, which are the components of lectin pathway, are produced in the liver in response to the infection.",
      "C": "The complement inhibitor, such as C3b, is only produced in the host cell but no in the bacteria, which is why the complement selectively kills the microbes."
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "4. (B)\n(A) Clr 和 C1s 與 MASP1、MASP2 結構相近。MBL 則是結構與 C1q 相近。\n(B) 正確。\n(C) C3b 不是 inhibitor。Inhibitor (調節蛋白) 是 CR1、H，只有一般細胞上有。\n(D) C3a、C5a 能促進吞噬細胞移動到感染、發炎區域。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "TNF-α is a proinflammatory cytokine that acts on endothelial cells, skeleton muscle, and the heart to trigger different effects, which is the pleiotropic effect of cytokines.",
      "B": "IL-6 can trigger acute phase response through binding to kidney.",
      "C": "IFN-Is, including IFN-α, IFN-β, IFN-γ, induced by TLR-3 and TLR-7 signaling pathway are critical to triggering antiviral response.",
      "D": "LPS-induced overproduction of IL-6 during systemic bacterial infection can trigger disseminated intravascular coagulation and multiorgan failure, which is called endotoxic shock."
    },
    "answer": ["A", "D"],
    "explanation": "5. (A)(D)\n(A) Correct.\n(B) IL-6 triggers acute phase responses through binding to hepatocytes (liver).\n(C) IFN-Is (IFN-α and IFN-β) are primarily induced by TLR-3 and TLR-7 signaling pathways and trigger antiviral response. IFN-γ (Type II IFN) is induced by TLR-4 signaling pathway triggered by the LPS of Gram-negative bacteria.\n(D) Correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement concerning TLR is correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "TLRs are expressed on plasma membrane, endosome and cytosol, to recognize PAMPs and trigger acute responses.",
      "B": "Except for TLR4, all other TLRs signal through MyD88, an adaptor molecule.",
      "C": "TLRs are single-pass transmembrane protein with leucine-rich repeat that recognize PAMPs.",
      "D": "TLR3 recognizes dsRNA, which is a PAMP of the virus genome, in cytosol."
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "6. (C)\n(A) TLRs are only expressed on plasma membrane and endosome.\n(B) Except for TLR3, all other TLRs signal through MyD88.\n(C) Correct.\n(D) TLR3 which binds dsRNA is located in endosome."
  },
  {
    "question": "Macrophage and neutrophil are phagocytes, which of the followings is correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Both can produce lysozyme to dissolve LPS of the Gram-negative G (-) bacterial cell wall.",
      "B": "Macrophage can produce lactoferrin, which competes Fe2+, which is a necessary ion for bacterial replication.",
      "C": "Upon bacterial infection, neutrophil can undergo NETosis to form extracellular trap (NET), in which releases its nuclear chromatin, trapping but not kill pathogens.",
      "D": "Neutrophils tracks down bacteria with G-protein coupled receptors that sense fMLF which is a peptide specific to bacteria."
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "7. (D)\n(A) Both produce Lysozyme which digests cell walls of some Gram-positive bacteria.\n(B) Neutrophil can produce lactoferrin which competes Fe2+.\n(C) NETs contain elastase, myelo-peroxidase, cathepsin G and lactoferrin which degrade or block pathogens.\n(D) Correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "Clonal Selection Theory (CST) is the foundation of adaptive immunity. Which statement concerning CST is correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "CST explains self-tolerance because self-reactive T and B lymphocytes are deleted in the bone marrow.",
      "B": "Based on CST, tissues can be successfully transplanted into foreign recipients when recipient's immune system is mature.",
      "C": "CST explains antigen specificity because each lymphocyte expresses a distinct antigen receptor, and only lymphocytes that react with a given antigen can undergo expansion.",
      "D": "Dr. Peter Medawar first hypothesized CST and received the Nobel Prize later."
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "8. (C)\n(A) Self-reactive T lymphocytes are deleted in the thymus.\n(B) The success of tissue transplantation depends on factors beyond CST, such as histocompatibility and immune suppression.\n(C) Correct.\n(D) CST was first proposed by Dr. Macfarlane Burnet (who later jointly received the Nobel Prize with Dr. Peter Medawar for the discovery of acquired immunological tolerance)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Presentation of pre-B receptor is an important checkpoint in B cell development. Which statement concerning signal from pre-B receptor is CORRECT?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Will inhibit light chain gene rearrangement.",
      "B": "Will promote heavy chain gene rearrangement.",
      "C": "Will promote surrogate light gene rearrangement.",
      "D": "Will enhance pre-B cell proliferation."
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "9. (D)\n(A) 應為 PROMOTE light chain gene rearrangement"
  },
  {
    "question": "The vaccination method invented by Dr. Jenner and the variolation method by Chinese doctor both induce immunity against smallpox. Which is correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "The reason vaccination works is because the virus that cause cowpox is the same as smallpox.",
      "B": "Theoretically, the efficiency of the immunity cause by variolation is better than vaccination.",
      "C": "Because of the invention of vaccination, smallpox was eradicated within 50 years after its invention.",
      "D": "The side effect of variolation could have been avoided if the inoculation had been via the subcutaneous route like vaccination instead of nasal route."
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "10. (B)\n(A) 不會是一模一樣，是因兩種病毒關係相近，表面具有相似抗原，故對牛痘產生的抗體也能有效對抗天花。\n(B) 因是天然未減毒的病毒株接種，所以引起免疫的效率確實比較好。\n(C) 牛痘疫苗在 1796 年由 Dr. Jenner 發明，但天花一直到 1979 年才由 WHO 宣布根除，所以大概過了 183 年。\n(D) 人痘接種 (variolation) 之風險來自於天然未減毒的病毒株直接接種，而非接種方式引起。"
  },
  {
    "question": "The development of T and B lymphocytes share some common features. Which statement concerning lymphocyte development is correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "The anatomic site of rearrangement of antigen receptor genes of both T and B lymphocyte is located in the bone marrow.",
      "B": "The heavy chain genes of BCR are an evolutionary resemblance to the alpha chain of TCR.",
      "C": "The selection process for self antigen recognition of both T and B lymphocytes does not occur until it reaches the immature lymphocyte stage.",
      "D": "There are two checkpoints to ensure the rearrangement of antigen receptor genes of both lymphocytes is successful and non-self-reactive."
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "11. (C)\n(A) 在 rearrangement of antigen receptor genes 階段，兩者各自位在 generative organ (骨髓 / 胸腺 )。(B11 vol.1 第 76 頁)\n(B) Pre-BCR 之替代輕鏈與 pre-TCR 之替代 alpha 鏈演化上相似。\n(C) 接受過自體抗原受體檢查後，前驅 B 細胞才能發育為未成熟 B 細胞。題目有點繞口，直到未成熟階段前都不會開始 = 成熟階段前才開始。\n(D) 是三道檢查點 (必考，忘了請複習 B11 vol.1 第 77 頁)。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about B cell development is correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "BCR starts to rearrange DH and JH at pro-B stage in two chromosomes.",
      "B": "BCR rearranges VH to DJH at pre-B, but doesn't express antigen receptor because light chain hasn't arranged.",
      "C": "Mature B class switch from IgM to IgD.",
      "D": "After selection, all B that express over affinity to self-antigens are rendered to apoptotic."
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "12. (A)\n(A) 正確。(詳細可看 B11 vol.1 第 86 頁)\n(B) 在小 pre B 細胞階段時，輕鏈的 V-J 重排已完成，因而能做接下來的自體抗原測試。\n(C) IgM 並未消失，而是多了 IgD 表現。\n(D) 並非所有未通過自體抗原測試的 B cell 都會被凋亡，可透過挽救機制：receptor editing 重新基因重組。(詳細可看 B11 vol.1 第 87 頁，自體反應 B 細胞的 4 種命運)。"
  },
  {
    "question": "During an infection, antigen-presenting cells, such as dendritic cells, pick up antigens at ______ activate adaptive immunity at ______ Then the activated T cells, B cells and antibodies eliminate pathogens at ______?",
    "options": {
      "A": "the site of infection; secondary lymphoid organs; secondary lymphoid organs",
      "B": "the site of infection; secondary lymphoid organs; the site of infection",
      "C": "the site of infection; the site of infection; the site of infection",
      "D": "secondary lymphoid organs; the site of infection; the site of infection",
      "E": "secondary lymphoid organs; secondary lymphoid organs; the site of infection"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "1. (B)\n淋巴球離開主要淋巴組織 (central lymphoid organs) 後，進入血液循環並進入周圍淋巴組織 (peripheral lymphoid organs)，包括淋巴結、脾臟、腸淋巴組織等次級淋巴組織。\nDendritic cells 會在感染之處遇見病原體、抗原，將其吞噬形成抗原呈現細胞，而周邊淋巴組織 (主要為淋巴結) 為 B cell 被抗原活化之處，B cell、antibodies 最後透過血液或淋巴循環抵達感染的地方與清除病原體，如下圖。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statement regarding ILCs is not correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "ILCs are innate cells and are derived from CLP in bone marrow.",
      "B": "ILCs don't present T cell receptor or B cell receptor.",
      "C": "ILCs produce cytokines overlapping with CD4 T cells or CD8 T cell.",
      "D": "ILC2 produce IFN-gamma to eliminate extracellular bacteria and fungi.",
      "E": "ILC3 produce IL-17 and IL-22 to recruit and activate neutrophil."
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "2. (D)\n(A) ILCs 是先天淋巴細胞 (innate)，與其它淋巴細胞一樣在骨髓生成 (lymphoid lineage)，並分佈於淋巴結與具有表皮組織的器官。\n(B) 非 T 細胞亦非 B 細胞 (沒有 TCR，也沒有 BCR)，沒有抗原專一。\n(C) ILCs 與對應的 T 細胞有類似的功能 (overlapping cytokines)。\n(D) 第三類免疫反應 (type 3 response) 針對胞外細菌及真菌，ILC3 可製造 IL-17 and IL-22 吸引與激活嗜中性球。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following about T cell is NOT correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "TH1: intracellular pathogen: activate macrophage",
      "B": "TH2: helminth: tissue repair",
      "C": "TFH: extracellular bacteria and fungi: TNF-α",
      "D": "Treg: inhibit T cell function: IL-10 and TGF-β",
      "E": "Cytotoxic T cell: virus-infected cell: perforin and granzyme"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "3. (C)\n(A) TH1 主要對付生長在巨噬細胞中的細菌，TH1 細胞辨認病原後被活化，分泌細胞介素 IFN-γ 傳遞訊號。訊傳入巨噬細胞後會促使溶酶體 (lysosome) 和吞噬小體 (phagosome) 結合，形成吞噬溶酶體 (phagolysosome)，活化巨噬細胞消滅外來病原。\n(B) TH2 對付胞外寄生蟲感染 (helminth: 蠕蟲)，並分泌 IL-4、IL-13，活化 M2 巨噬細胞，幫助組織修復。\n(C) TFH 位於 B 細胞濾泡 (follicle)，主要負責幫助 B 細胞的生發中心 (GC) 成熟。\nextracellular bacteria and fungi 是 type 3 response，immune effector module 包含 group 3 ILCs、TH17 CD4+ T cell、IgG1、IgG2、嗜中性球。TNF-α 由被 TH1 活化的巨噬細胞所產生。兩者皆非 TFH 主導。\n(D) Treg 可分泌 inhibitory cytokines (IL-10、TGF-β) 抑制免疫系統。\n(E) 胞毒性 T 細胞可清除被病毒感染的細胞，分泌穿孔素 (perforin) 使細胞穿孔、分泌顆粒酶 (granzyme) 使細胞內部物質被分解，進而發生細胞凋亡。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is NOT correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "During latency, viruses persist in the host and can be reactivate when the host's immune system is compromised.",
      "B": "Antibody against one serotype of Streptococcus pneumoniae can protect against another serotype.",
      "C": "Inherited genetic defect in T cell development can result in defects in other components of the immune system.",
      "D": "Some intracellular infection like Mycobacterium tuberculosis cannot be completely removed.",
      "E": "X-linked SCID is an immunodeficiency of IL-2RG, causing problem on IL-2R and affect immune system."
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "4. (B)\n(A) 免疫反應進程中的 latent infection (潛伏感染)：病原體並未在個體呈現出明顯病理反應及相關病原分泌物，但若免疫力降低時便會產生病理反應。\n(B) 免疫系統產生的抗體具有血清型特異性 (serotype-specific)，而肺炎鏈球菌中構成莢膜的多醣只要稍微改變就會形成新的 serotype，無法被過去感染的記憶細胞辨識。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statement is NOT correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Desensitization is the therapy that to restore tolerance to the allergen by reducing its tendency to induce IgE production.",
      "B": "Delayed-type hypersensitivity (DTH) is mediated by B cells.",
      "C": "Anaphylactic shock is caused by IgE secreted by mast cells systematically.",
      "D": "Celiac disease is a type of hypersensitivity caused by gluten in the food.",
      "E": "The response caused by antigens in immunology can be either immediate or delayed."
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "5. (B)\n(A) 減敏治療 (desensitization)：暴露低劑量的過敏原，並逐步增加劑量，讓免疫系統慢慢忍受過敏原，減少誘發 IgE 產生。\n(B) 過敏可依反應時間分為 2 類：立即型與延遲型 (DTH)。DTH 由 T 細胞調控，接觸到過敏原後兩三天才出現過敏反應。\n(C) 第一型過敏反應，肥大細胞活化後造成組織胺和其他媒介物遍布，血流及血管通透性 (permeability) 增加，體液外流到組織液中、血壓降低，輕則可能產生蕁麻疹 (urticaria)，重則過敏性休克 (anaphylactic shock)。\n(D) 麩質敏感性腸疾 / 乳糜瀉 (gluten-sensitive enteropathy/celiac disease)：攝取小麥穀蛋白或其他穀物的類似蛋白質，誘發 T 細胞去攻擊腸細胞，造成上皮細胞受傷。\n(E) 同 (B)。"
  },
  {
    "question": "All of the following are tenets of the hygiene hypothesis except",
    "options": {
      "A": "a decrease in allergic disease in developed countries compared to developing countries.",
      "B": "widespread use of antibiotics interferes with the use and education of the immune system.",
      "C": "widespread immunization practices compromise the development of a fully functional immune response.",
      "D": "childhood exposure to microorganisms is reduced.",
      "E": "antibiotic-driven selection of super bacteria perturbs the immune system."
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "6. (A)\n(A) 過敏反應在進步國家的發生率較發展中國家高。\n(B) 正確。\n(C) 正確。\n(D) 正確。\n(E) 正確。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Allergy and autoimmunity are caused by abnormal immune responses that are against appropriate antigens.",
    "options": {
      "T": "True",
      "F": "False"
    },
    "answer": "F",
    "explanation": "1. F\n當後天免疫系統對於「無害抗原」起不適當的反應時，就會導致過敏，包含過敏症和自體免疫，而過敏案例通常複雜，可能結合多種機轉類型。(B10 共筆 Vol.4 p.14)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Inflammation is harmful so it needs to be avoided in all stages of immunity.",
    "options": {
      "T": "True",
      "F": "False"
    },
    "answer": "F",
    "explanation": "2. F\n發炎是免疫反應的重要組成部分，有助於保護身體免受感染和損傷，有助於清除有害刺激，啟動治癒過程、對抗病原體。然而過度或持續的發炎確實可能是有害的，並導致各種疾病。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Type 1 hypersensitivity reaction is caused by an IgG-mediated immune response whose main physiological role is to defend against parasite infection.",
    "options": {
      "T": "True",
      "F": "False"
    },
    "answer": "F",
    "explanation": "3. F\nType 1 hypersensitivity reaction is caused by an IgE-mediated immune response whose main physiological role is to defend against parasite infection.\n在組織中，IgE 與肥大細胞 (mast cell) 的 FcεRI 結合並活化之造成過敏；在血液中則結合嗜鹼性球 (basophil) 的 FcεRI。(B10 共筆 Vol.4 p.14)"
  },
  {
    "question": "以下關於 T cell immune tolerance 的機制何者有誤?",
    "options": {
      "A": "central tolerance",
      "B": "anergy",
      "C": "presence of regulatory T cell",
      "D": "receptor editing"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "1. (D)\n身體會藉由中樞耐受性 (central tolerance) 和周圍耐受性 (peripheral tolerance) 避免自體免疫的發生。\n中樞耐受性 (central tolerance)：B 細胞和 T 細胞在中樞淋巴器官發育時，藉由負選擇去除大多數會攻擊身體的細胞，少數進到周邊區域。\n周圍耐受性 (peripheral tolerance)：在淋巴球成熟後進入次級淋巴器官時進行。對於少數仍有自體免疫的淋巴細胞，藉由細胞失能 (anergy)、Treg 細胞調節 (抑制或分化成 Treg)、細胞凋亡 (apoptosis)，或利用免疫豁免位置 (immunologically privileged site) 使其不能接觸到自身抗原等方式，避免自體免疫。\nAnergy: 沒有 CD28 這些 signal 存在時，T cell 沒辦法產生足夠的 IL-2"
  },
  {
    "question": "關於 solid organ transplantation 的治療藥物標的, 針對抑制 T 細胞活化, 以下何者正確?",
    "options": {
      "A": "cyclosporine 和 tacrolimus 主要是抑制 calcineurin, 進而抑制 T cell 活化的訊息傳遞, 進一步阻礙 IL-2 產生。",
      "B": "rapamycin 抑制 mTOR 分子, 進而抑制 T cell 活化和增生。",
      "C": "Basiliximab 單株抗體直接和 T cell 表面的 IL-2 接受器結合, 抑制 T cell 活化。",
      "D": "以上皆是。"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "2. (D)\n抗排斥藥物 (immunosuppressive drug)：以抑制 T 細胞活化為主。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Immunity signal ligand to inhibit CD8 T cell?",
    "options": {
      "A": "MHC I",
      "B": "MHC II",
      "C": "PD-1",
      "D": "CD28",
      "E": "PD-L1"
    },
    "answer": "E",
    "explanation": "1. (E)\n舉例來說，腫瘤細胞表面表現的 PD-L1 可與 T cell 上的 PD-1 結合，抑制 T cell 的活化。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is the best description for the rearrangement of T cell receptor alpha chain during the T cell development?",
    "options": {
      "A": "In the mature T cell.",
      "B": "After binding to self-antigen.",
      "C": "Before CD3+ T cell.",
      "D": "In the double negative stage.",
      "E": "In the double positive stage."
    },
    "answer": "E",
    "explanation": "2. (E)\nBeta 鏈重組發生在 double negative 的 DN1、DN2 期，DN3、DN4 期則不發生重組。\nAlpha 鏈重組發生在 double positive 期。\nRAG-1 及 RAG-2 重組酶參與 TCR alpha, beta 鏈的基因重組。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is not associated with negative choice?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Self tolerance",
      "B": "Thymic medullary epithelial cell",
      "C": "Recognition of self antigen",
      "D": "Recognition of foreign antigen",
      "E": "Apoptosis"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "3. (D)\n發育中的 T cell 若與自身抗原受體產生高強度結合 (high avidity) 反應，則進行淘汰。\n負選擇在 thymocyte 位於胸腺皮質時即開始，在胸腺皮質和髓質都會發生，但整體而言先做正選擇再做負選擇。\n負選擇和多種能進行抗原呈現的細胞有關，包含胸腺的皮質上皮細胞 (cortical epithelial cell)、髓質上皮細胞 (medullary epithelial cell) 或源於骨髓的抗原呈現細胞 (bone marrow derived APCs) 如髓質樹突細胞、巨噬細胞等以上三種細胞。\nNegative choice 的意義在於排除 auto immune。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is not associated with positive choice?",
    "options": {
      "A": "決定發育成 CD4 or CD8",
      "B": "對自體抗原產生辨識可存活。",
      "C": "對自體抗原辨識太過強烈則會發生細胞凋亡。"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "4. (C)\n無法辨識自身 MHC 抗原的 T cell 會死亡。\n正選擇發生在胸腺皮質上皮細胞 (thymic cortical epithelial cell) 處，主要由皮質間質細胞 (epithelial stroma cell) 進行 MHC 抗原呈現供 T cell 辨識。\n正選擇同時會決定 T cell 的後續分化，當 T cell 與兩種 MHC 之一的結合度較高，會誘導對應轉錄因子的產生，決定其輔助受體特異性，即 transcriptional programming。\n正選擇訊號的產生需要 TCR 以及 CD4, CD8 co-receptor 合作產生 Positive choice 的意義在於 MHC restriction。"
  },
  {
    "question": "下列那個分子在胸腺表現周邊組織的抗原以進行負選擇?",
    "options": {
      "A": "TdT",
      "B": "AIRE",
      "C": "ID2",
      "D": "IL2",
      "E": "TECK"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "5. (B)\n自體免疫調節因子 (AIRE, autoimmune regulator) 在胸腺髓質中表現，誘發一般在周圍組織上才表現的蛋白質之表現，幫助負選擇進行。(共筆 vol2 P65)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is not the antigens recognized by T cells?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Most T cells recognize peptides and no other molecules.",
      "B": "T cells recognize conformational determinants of protein antigen.",
      "C": "CD4+ and CD8+ T cells preferentially recognize antigens from extracellular environment into vesicles and antigens in cytosol, respectively.",
      "D": "T cells ...",
      "E": "T cell receptors recognize only one determinant from antigens."
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "6. (B)\nT 細胞辨識的是線性多肽。因為只有線性多肽才與 MHC 的 clefts 結合，且與 MHC 結合的多肽在形成時，便已經喪失了蛋白質的構型。(共筆 vol2 P75)"
  },
  {
    "question": "During V(D)J recombination of lymphocytes, recombination signal sequences are recognized by which of the following?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Receptor tyrosine kinase",
      "B": "Constant region",
      "C": "Leading region",
      "D": "RAG-1 / RAG-2 enzymes",
      "E": "Diversity region"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "7. (D)\nRAG-1 (Recombination-activating gene - 1) / RAG-2 複合物會與 recombination signal sequence (RSS) 結合並切割。以進行 RAG- dependent V(D)J rearrangement。(共筆 vol2 P97)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following features is the characteristic of class II MHC pathway of antigen processing and presentation?",
    "options": {
      "A": "B1, B2 and β5 subunits of proteasomes are responsible for protein degradation.",
      "B": "CD8+ T cells are responsive T cells.",
      "C": "Endoplasmic reticulum (ER) is the site of peptide loading to MHC.",
      "D": "Late endosomes and lysosomes are the site of antigen degradation.",
      "E": "TAP1/2 molecules are involved in peptide transport and loading."
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "8. (D)\n(A) 為 class I MHC 組裝過程。\n(B) 應為 CD4+。\n(C) 在 lysosome 裡進行結合。\n(D) 正確。\n(E) 為 class I MHC 組裝過程。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements regarding the sequence of cancer cell editing is correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Escape, Elimination, Equilibrium",
      "B": "Equilibrium, Elimination, Escape",
      "C": "Elimination, Equilibrium, Escape",
      "D": "Elimination, Escape, Equilibrium",
      "E": "Equilibrium, Escape, Elimination"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "9. (C)\n腫瘤的演化分為三階段，其順序為清除 (Elimination)、平衡 (Equilibrium)、逃脫 (Escape)，故答案選 (C)。\n以下為此三階段的詳細說明。(1) 清除 (elimination)：正常細胞癌化成腫瘤細胞時表現出腫瘤特定抗原 (TSA, tumor-specific antigen)，被免疫系統辨識並清除 (immune surveillance)。(2) 平衡 (equilibrium)：還未被清除的腫瘤細胞一面突變、生長，一面和免疫系統對抗，增減維持一定平衡。(3) 逃脫 (escape)：不斷突變的結果，出現能逃過免疫系統辨識的細胞，開始不受控制生長，形成腫瘤。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT a component of immunological synapse?",
    "options": {
      "A": "LFA-1",
      "B": "B7",
      "C": "MHC",
      "D": "TLR",
      "E": "TCR"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "10. (D)\nImmunological synapse 可以分為兩個部分，核心處為 cSMAC，周圍為 pSMAC。(1) cSMAC：除了具有 T 細胞上的 TCR complex、CD4 以及 APC 上的 MHC，還分佈有其他 costimulatory molecules，例如在 T 細胞上有 CD28、CD2 可以分別與 APC 上的 B7.1 (又稱 CD80)、B7.2 (又稱 CD86) 與 LFA-3 結合，這些都隸屬 cSMAC 的範圍。(2) pSMA：在 T 細胞上由 LFA-1，APC 上由 ICAM-1 組成，兩者有交互作用。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT a characteristic of cold tumor?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Exclusion of CD8+ T cells and NK cells from the tumor.",
      "B": "Low antigen presentation.",
      "C": "Immunosuppressive immune cells in tumor (ex. Tregs, MDSC).",
      "D": "Poor prognosis and response to immunotherapy.",
      "E": "Elevated effector cytokine, such as Granzyme B."
    },
    "answer": "E",
    "explanation": "11. (E)\n(A)(B)(C)(D) 皆為 cold tumor 的特性，而 (E) 選項之描述為 hot tumor 的特性 (詳見 B10 共筆 Vol. 4 p.44)。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements regarding T cell-mediated cytotoxicity is correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Cytotoxic T cells induce the senescence of target cells.",
      "B": "Cytotoxic T cells induce cytotoxic T cell apoptosis.",
      "C": "Cytotoxic T cells 透過 FAS/FAS-L 的 interaction 使 target cell 死亡。",
      "D": "Cytotoxic T cells induce shed of membrane-bound vesicle and shrink of target cell.",
      "E": "Cytotoxic T cells release granzymes and perforin."
    },
    "answer": ["C", "E"],
    "explanation": "12. (C)(E)\n(C)(E) 正確，可參見 B10 共筆 Vol. 3 p.26。(B) 應為 Cytotoxic T cells induce target cell apoptosis。"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many polypeptide chain(s) is(are) in an IgG antibody?",
    "options": {
      "A": "one",
      "B": "two",
      "C": "three",
      "D": "four"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "1. (D)\n重鏈及輕鏈各兩條組成了免疫球蛋白的 Y 字型結構，包含兩條臂 (arm) 及一個主幹 (trunk)。(共筆 vol2 P10)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following enzyme can cleave an antibody into two Fab fragments and one Fc fragment?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Pepsin",
      "B": "C3 convertase",
      "C": "Trypsin",
      "D": "Papain"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "2. (D)\n木瓜酵素 (papain)：切在兩重鏈之間雙硫鍵的 N 端，產生兩條 Fab 及一條 Fc，同時雙硫鍵仍留在 Fc 上。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is NOT involved in IgG transfer across the placenta?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Neonatal of Fc receptor",
      "B": "Fc Portion of IgG",
      "C": "MHC class I molecule",
      "D": "Endosome"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": null
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is not correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Antibody can recognize discontinuous peptide chain, which also called linear epitope.",
      "B": "Hyper variable region is determined by both V regions of heavy chain and light chain.",
      "C": "Hyper variable region is also called complementary determining region.",
      "D": "Antibody usually recognize small part of a large molecule, which can be polysaccharide or proteins."
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "4. (A)\n(A) 應為 continuous。\n可以將 epitope 分為：\n1. Conformational epitope：抗原決定位有多個，分布在三維空間中。例如：一條折疊的多肽上有三個不相臨的胺基酸可以被抗體辨識。\n2. Linear epitope：抗原決定位位於一連續線型的分子構造中。例如：一條多肽上有一串連續的胺基酸可以被抗體辨識。(共筆 vol2 P19)\n(B) (共筆 vol2 P15)\n(C) 圈環作為互補性決定區 (CDRs)，是辨識抗原的重要區域。六個 HV 圈環共同決定了一個抗原的結合位。(共筆 vol2 P15)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one does not involve in the structure -based analysis of antigen-antibody complex?",
    "options": {
      "A": "monoclonal antibody",
      "B": "Fc region antibody",
      "C": "X-ray crystallography",
      "D": "Epitope"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "5. (B)\nAntibody 的 Fc region 並未與 antigen 結合。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which does not happen in the B cell germinal center?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Somatic hypermutation",
      "B": "Pre-B rearrangement",
      "C": "Affinity maturation",
      "D": "Isotype switch"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "6. (B)\n(A)(C)(D) 發生在 germinal center 的事件，通稱為 germinal center reaction，如體細胞高度變異 (somatic hypermutation)、抗體類型轉換重組 (class switch recombination)、親和力成熟 (affinity maturation)。(詳見免疫學 B11 共筆 Vol 2 第 35 頁)"
  },
  {
    "question": "下列何者為 TI-1?",
    "options": {
      "A": "virus HА",
      "B": "bacterial polysaccharide",
      "C": "diphtheria toxin",
      "D": "bacterial lipopolysaccharide"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "7. (D)\n依抗原是否可以和 BCR crosslink，分為 TI-1 和 TI-2，TI-1 不可以，TI-2 可以。(TI-1 與 TI-2 例子詳見免疫學 B11 共筆第 42 頁表格)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following vaccines administrated in Taiwan is live-attenuated vaccine?",
    "options": {
      "A": "pneumococcal conjugate vaccine",
      "B": "human papilloma virus vaccine",
      "C": "measles, mumps, and rubella vaccine",
      "D": "seasonal influenza vaccine"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "8. (C)\n(A) 13 價結合型肺炎鏈球菌疫苗，不活化疫苗。\n(B) 人類乳突病毒疫苗，不活化疫苗。\n(C) 麻疹腮腺炎德國麻疹混合疫苗，減毒疫苗。\n(D) 季節性流感疫苗，不活化疫苗。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which following about vaccines are not correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "There are still infections for which there is no effective vaccines available yet.",
      "B": "Most vaccines generate antibodies that prevent damages from toxins or that neutralize pathogens and stop infection.",
      "C": "Polio vaccines usually induce protective T cell rather than antibodies.",
      "D": "Live-attenuated vaccines are theoretically more potent than killed vaccines."
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "9. (C)\n小兒麻痺病毒疫苗為不活化疫苗 (inactivated polio vaccine)，可以產生對抗病毒的抗體，可以防止小兒麻痺侵入中樞神經以及防止癱瘓。\nReference: IPV – GPEI (polioeradication.org)"
  },
  {
    "question": "下列何者不是 FDA approved adjuvant?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Flagellin",
      "B": "Alum",
      "C": "Squalene and water emulsion",
      "D": "cpg1018"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "10. (A)\n(A) 不在名單中。\n(B) alum 為鉀鋁硫酸 (Potassium Aluminum Sulfate)，鋁鹽為常見的佐劑，廣泛用於許多疫苗中——數量太多族繁不及備載，故不一一列出。鋁鹽的功能目前眾說紛紜，較為人接受的解釋為鋁鹽可以協助吸附、逐步釋放抗原，而近期也有研究指出鋁鹽可以刺激免疫細胞 (包括巨噬細胞、樹突細胞)，可以調節免疫功能。\n(C) 此類佐劑為透過調節疫苗傳送系統的釋放效果增進疫苗的效力。大致上為使疫苗被油脂包裹住，使其能夠被油脂保護住直到被吞噬細胞吞噬。這種配方被稱為 MF59，是透過角鯊烯與水形成乳液懸滴，使其能夠被吞噬細胞有效吞噬。\n(D) 此類佐劑為增進免疫誘導力，透過 TLR-9 與 CpG 的結合，誘導吞噬細胞吞入疫苗以促進疫苗的效力。"
  },
  {
    "question": "下列何者錯誤?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Th17 分泌 IL-17, IL-22",
      "B": "Th2 分泌 IFN-γ 刺激發炎反應",
      "C": "亡佚",
      "D": "亡佚"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "11. (B)\nTh2 為特化的 effector T cell，是用以對抗寄生蟲 (parasites)、蠕蟲 (helminths) 的手段，會透過分泌 IL-4、IL-13 進而誘導嗜酸性球、嗜鹼性球、肥大細胞作用。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following does not involve in the production of CAR-T(CART-19)",
    "options": {
      "A": "retrovirus",
      "B": "CD16",
      "C": "4-1BB",
      "D": "CD3ζ"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "12. (B)\nCAR-T 仰賴基因工程，利用 Lentivirus (一種反轉錄病毒) 使表現謙和抗原受體——可引導基因編輯後的 T 細胞找到癌細胞——後在送回體內。\n後的嵌合抗原受體包刮 Costimulatory domain，如 CD28、4-1BB，以及 signal domain，如 CD3ζ。"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is not correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "peptide-based vaccine 是一種策略用以辨識 B cell 的 peptide 以促進免疫反應",
      "B": "live attenuated 可以透過 DNA recombinant 來達成",
      "C": "conjugated vaccine 的進展有助於流感防治",
      "D": "亡佚"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "13. (B)\n正確的說法應該是，活性減毒疫苗通常是通過減毒過程製造的，這個過程中，病原體會被削弱，但它仍然是活著的。\n這種減毒可以通過各種方法來實現，例如 serial passage 或特定基因突變。\nDNA recombinant 技術通常用於製 subunit vaccines or DNA vaccines，而不是 live attenuated 疫苗。\n(來源：網路資料，因未在共筆中找到此資訊)"
  }
]
